Guide to the Elizabeth J. Somers papers and memorabilia, 1862-1998 MVC0007.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Elizabeth J. Somers papers and memorabilia
1862-1998
1880-1895
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0007.MS
5.75 Linear Feet 1 slim document box, 2 document boxes, 2 oversized flat boxes, 2 small flat boxes
Elizabeth J. Somers (1837-1924) founded the Mount Vernon Seminary in Washington, D.C. in 1875. Mount Vernon Seminary and College merged with The George Washington University in 1999. This collection contains correspondence, photographs (some reproductions), negatives, photocopies, financial records, and textiles related to Elizabeth J. Somers from the years 1862 to 1998. The bulk of the material is from 1881 to 1895, particularly on the first two locations of Mount Vernon Seminary at 204 F Street, NW and 1100 M Street, NW. Also present are images and biographical information on Somers, and historical information on Mount Vernon Seminary.
Biographical / Historical
Elizabeth J. Somers (1837-1924) founded the Mount Vernon Seminary in Washington, D.C. in 1875. Elizabeth Somers was born Elizabeth Jane ("Jennie") Eddy on November 5th, 1837 in Rush County, Indiana. Elizabeth attended Ohio Wesleyan Female College and graduated in 1855 with the degree of Mistress of English Literature. After graduating, Elizabeth accepted a position at Northwestern Female College in Evanston, Illinois and left in 1859 for a position at Pittsburgh Female Seminary where she worked for two years. She then worked at Centerville, Indiana from 1862 to 1863.
Elizabeth married James W. Somers, a lawyer, in early 1863 and left a teaching position in Centerville, Indiana to move to Washington, D.C. Somers continued her career teaching mathematics at a day school and bible classes at the Metropolitan Methodist Church. In 1868, Somers' accepted Judge Dennis Nelson Cooley's three young daughters as her first students in her home on 204 F. Street, NW in Washington, D.C. She began teaching boys and girls but by 1870, Somers only offered instruction to young women.
In 1875, Somers opened the Mount Vernon Seminary with a rigorous curriculum for girls as well as young women preparing for college. At the time, Elizabeth Somers offered the only higher education institution for women in Washington, D.C. Mount Vernon Seminary quickly earned an esteemed reputation for the refined academic and social education of young women in Washington, D.C. that first attracted prominent Washington officials' daughters but soon also many young women from around the world.
Elizabeth Somers' school was named Mount Vernon Seminary in honor of her late brother, Dr. Thomas Eddy, a respected Methodist minister, who helped build the Mount Vernon Methodist Church in Baltimore, Maryland. In 1880, Somers moved the school from 201 F Street, NW to 1100 M Street, NW to meet the demands of increasing enrollment. The school remained at 1100 M Street until 1917 and underwent numerous physical expansions as it accepted more students. Mrs. Somers would later move the school again to Nebraska Avenue in 1917. In 1927, Mount Vernon Seminary included a Junior College and by 1969 was known as Mount Vernon Junior College. The school became an accredited four-year college in 1976. Mount Vernon College relocated a couple of times more until it merged with The George Washington University in 1999 and is now known as the Mount Vernon Campus.
Elizabeth J. Somers died on June 8th, 1924 and was buried in Indianapolis, Indiana.
In 1945, Somers Hall was built on Mount Vernon Campus and now houses the women of the selective Elizabeth Somers Women's Leadership Program. The Elizabeth Somers Women's Leadership Program was established for freshman undergraduate women of The George Washington University to continue Somers' vision of excellence and leadership of women.
Separated Materials
Elizabeth J. Somers' personal copy of a volume titled "Defenders of Democracy: Contributions from represeentative men and women of letters and other arts from our allies and our own country" as Editted by The Gift Book Committee of the Militia of Mercy (John Lane Company, 1918) was transferred from this collection to be cataloged and integrated into the Special Collections Research Center's book collection.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into six series: Biographical Information, Mount Vernon Seminary Historical Information, Images, Textiles, Flatware, and Artifacts.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, photographs (some reproductions), negatives, photocopies, notes, financial records, commencement attire, silverware, and a dress worn by Elizabeth Somers. The collection contains material from the years 1862 to 1998 and the bulk of the collection pertains to the years 1881 to 1895. The first two locations of Mount Vernon Seminary, 204 F Street, NW and 1100 M Street, NW are represented in this collection. Several images, invitations, and letters regarding Mount Vernon Seminary faculty, students, events, and early locations are present. Of particular interest to researchers are original letters from Elizabeth, negatives of Elizabeth Somers, a dress worn by Somers as seen in an Irving Wiles portrait, and letters from past graduates about Mrs. Somers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. Collection transferred to Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Related Materials note
The following contain additional information on Elizabeth J. Somers and Mount Vernon Seminary and College: "Dear Daughters: A History of Mount Vernon Sminary and College" by Nina Mikhalevsky (Mount Vernon Seminary and College Alumnae Association, 2001) and "Elizabeth J. Somers: A Memoir" by Faith Bradford (The Plimpton Press, 1937).
Bib#
8588635
Women -- Education; Women's colleges; George Washington University. Mount Vernon Campus; Eddy, Thomas Mears, Dr.; Mount Vernon Seminary; Wiles, Irving Ramsey; Somers, Elizabeth J.; Mount Vernon Methodist Church (Baltimore, Md.)
- Biographical Information, circa 1880-1994; Series 1; 5 folder(s)
  Arrangement
  Correspondence in this series is arranged chronologically. In the case of student memories, most did not include a date and are therefore arranged alphabetically according to students' names.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains letters from early graduates of the Mount Vernon Seminary recalling their memories of the school and particularly about Elizabeth Somers. Of particular interest to researchers are letters from Elizabeth Somers to others as well as letters from Elizabeth's relative chronicling the Eddy family's history. Several reproductions of Elizabeth J. Somers' portrait by Irving Wiles can be found here.
  - Life and History of Elizabeth Somers, 1935-1980; 1935-1936; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Student Memories of Elizabeth Somers, circa 1880-1934; 1934; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1862-1908; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Irving Wiles Portrait of Elizabeth Somers, 1918; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Elizabeth Somers" Mount Vernon College Press: A Series of Occassional Papers, Nina Mikhalevsky, Fall 1994; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Elizabeth Somers memoir by Faith Bradford [5 copies], 1937; Series 1 (Box 6)
  - Elizabeth Somers memoir by Faith Bradford [5 copies], 1937; Series 1 (Box 7)
  - "In Memorium: Elizabeth J. Somers and Adelia Gates Hensley", Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Order of Somers/Hensley memorial service and program, Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Mount Vernon Seminary Historical Information, 1881-1998; 1881-1895; Series 2; 4 folder(s)
  This series is arranged chronologically with undated material at the end of each folder.
  The materials in this series include historical information on Mount Vernon Seminary such as photocopied images of faculty, students, events, and the first two locations of the school. 204 F. Street, NW, and 1100 M. Street, NW. Historical background information on Mount Vernon Methodist Church, the church that Elizabeth Somers named her school after, can also be found in this series.
  - Faculty, Students, and Buildings, circa 1889; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Events, Publicity, and Financial Correspondence, 1882-1895; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Evening Star Newspaper, 6 December 1881; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mount Vernon Methodist Church, 1856-1998; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Images, Circa late 1880s - 1894; Series 3; 3 folder(s)
  Most material in this series is undated, therefore, Elizabeth Somers images are grouped by format before other images.
  This series contains photographs, negatives, photocopies, and image reproductions of Elizabeth Somers, her family members, and Mount Vernon Seminary events and associated individuals. Of particular interest are negatives of Elizabeth Somers as well as cyanotypes of her as well as her nephew as a child.
  - Photographs - Elizabeth Somers, circa late 1880s - 1894; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Reproductions of Elizabeth Somers Image, circa late 1880s; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mount Vernon Seminary, undated; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Textiles, circa 1918; Series 4; 3 artifact(s)
  Commencement textiles are housed in the same box. Elizabeth Somers' dress is housed separately.
  This series contains textiles owned and worn by Elizabeth Somers such as two commencement hoods, a commencement ribbon, and a dress as seen in the Irving Wiles portrait of Elizabeth Somers.
  - Red commencement hood, undated; Series 4 (Box 2)
  - Blue commencement hood, undated; Series 4 (Box 2)
  - Elizabeth Somers dress, 1918; Series 4 (Box 3)
- Flatware, 1891-1904; Series 5
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series contains silverware from the collection of Elizabeth J. Somers, including forks and spoons of varying sizes and styles. The items in this series range in date from 1891 to 1904.
  - 30 sterling silver dinner forks with "EJS" monogram, 1891; Series 5 (Box 4, Item 1)
    The inscription "Galt & Bro." on the back of the handle indicates that the spoons were produced by Galt & Bros., a company established in 1802 based in Washington, D.C.
    Another stamp reads Pat. 91, indicating the year the fork was produced (1891).
    see: http://www.replacements.com/webquote/DGADGA1.htm
  - 14 sterling silver teaspoons with "EJS" monogram, 1891; Series 5 (Box 4, Item 2)
    Another stamp reads Pat. 91, indicating the year the spoon was produced (1891).
  - 11 sterling silver teaspoons with "EJS" monogram, 1891; Series 5 (Box 4, Item 3)
    The lion and "W" in a circle on the handle indicate that these spoons were designed by the Whiting Manufacturing Company, formed in 1866 and bought by Gorham in 1924.
    This pattern is called Louis XV and was patented in 1891.
    One of the spoons is also stamped with "Galt & Bro." indicating that Galt & Bros., a company established in 1802 based in Washington, D.C. bought the forks from Whiting.
    The 10 other spoons are stamped with "M.W. Beveridge" likely standing for Michael William Beveridge, an importer and merchant based in Washington, D.C.
    see: http://www.925-1000.com/patterns_Whiting_4.html
  - 3 sterling silver serving spoons with "EJS" monogram, 1891; Series 5 (Box 4, Item 4)
  - 17 sterling silver salad forks with "EJS" monogram, 1900; Series 5 (Box 4, Item 5)
    The three hallmarks of the lion, anchor, and letter G on the back of the handle indicate that the design of the spoon was created by the Gorham Corporation in Providence, RI (founded circa 1815-1818). This pattern is called "Buttercup" and was first produced in 1899.
    The inscription "Galt & Bro." on the back of the handle indicates that Galt & Bros., a company established in 1802 based in Washington, D.C. bought the forks from Gorham and likely was the company that monogrammed it.
    Another stamp dates these spoons to 1900.
    see: http://www.silvercollection.it/dictionarypatterngorham.html
  - 24 sterling silver dinner forks with "EJS" monogram, 1900 (Box 4, Item 6)
    Another stamp dates these forks to 1900.
    see: http://www.silvercollection.it/gorham.html
  - 11 sterling silver soup spoons with "S" monogram, 1904; Series 5 (Box 4, Item 7)
    The hallmarks on the handle of these spoons indicate that it was manufactured by R.S. Wallace & Sons Manufacturing Company, based in Wallingford, CT and founded in 1871. The pattern of these spoons is called Violet and was patented in 1904.
    see: http://www.925-1000.com/patterns_Wallace_1.html see: http://www.925-1000.com/americansilver_W.html
- Artifacts, Series 6
  - Elizabeth Somers Chapel plaque, listing benefactors, Series 5; 1 Linear Feet (Box 5)
    Arranged as found.
    Contains one large plaque from the Elizabeth Somers Chapel indicating benefactors.